hello everyone welcome to actin flab
live stream number 25.2
today is july 13th 2021 and we're going
to be talking about this paper
the computational boundary of a self
developmental bioelectricity
drives multicellularity and skill free
cognition
we are here with the author mike levin
we are a participatory online lab
that is communicating learning and
practicing applied active inference
you can find us at the links here on
this page this is a recorded and an
archived live stream
so please provide us with feedback so
that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we will be following
good idiot video etiquette for live
streams
here at the short link you'll find all
the live streams that we've done so far
and we're going to have a new series of
live streams coming up
in the next semester
so we're going to be jumping off here
with the author
uh discussing this paper and we will
just do a brief round of introductions i
am blue knight and i am an independent
research consultant
based out of new mexico
uh yeah my name is sarah davis i'm a
master's philosophy student at this
point um past engineer and science
artist just generally interested
in how the world works michael
yeah i'm mike levin i'm a professor in
the biology department at tufts
university
i run the allen discovery center at
tufts and i'm also
a associate faculty at the peace
institute at harvard
cool so sarah what is something that
you're excited
to talk about today or something that
you'd like to remember about
the paper maybe want to give a heads up
um the most interesting kind of through
line for me
in in all of michael's work that i've
looked at is this
um connection or this um maybe tension
i don't know the way the the morphology
plays with electricity just um
yeah which one's in the driver's seat or
some kind of like understanding of
how those two work together
awesome is there any like burning
questions that you have that you want to
start off with
or otherwise i can just start oh no i
feel like that
is going to kind of happen down the road
that particular focus so
please yeah okay so here we are on the
paper we're going to be discussing today
how do multiple nested scales of
individuality
work yeah um
so i i want to preface this by saying
that and maybe maybe this is obvious but
i just want to say that
all of this is very much a work in
progress so i'm going to tell you what i
think about these things but
uh i certainly am not claiming that this
is all worked out or that i'm not going
to change my mind at some point
or uh you know that that this is not
going to develop in some
fashion this is under under um you know
constant constant work
so i think the
fundamentals of all this are simply that
there are multiple interpenetrating
systems at different scales that are all
present simultaneously
all of which can be profitably looked at
as
uh as as individuals and so this diagram
here
sort of it it looks like all it's saying
is the the mere
sort of fact of um physical structure if
you look you see organisms and within
that you've got organs and cells so
so that's not the you know that's sort
of not the whole point of this the point
isn't merely that they're arranged this
way
but that you've got some units and those
subunits have themselves subunits all of
which are
cells and what i mean by them being
cells is the central
claim of the paper is that they are to
some extent
so so not not binary but on a continuum
of agency they are to some extent goal
uh directed uh agents so they're trying
to achieve certain themes
and so when i say that they're nested
all of this simply means that you can
have systems
where the different parts are all
actively trying to achieve
various things in their own spaces and
we should talk about that that's an
important
part that developed since this paper was
written is this idea of different action
spaces that these things are working in
um but but they're nested in the sense
that i think
just because a higher level system
acquires a goal or is pursuing a goal
that doesn't mean the lower systems
aren't doing it and
uh all of these things are in fact
simultaneously doing their best to
pursue various kinds of goals
so that's what i meant by multiple
nested
individuals awesome
so is there a total 100 of individuality
that gets
partitioned and something that i've been
really interested in
is how is information passed forward and
backward across levels like is there
some kind of core screening
or um like salience
like dominates the information to pass
forward so how does that
kind of information flow work
yeah so so the scaling and the
relationship between layers is of course
one of the most interesting things here
so one of the things we are currently
trying to do
both experimentally and with modeling is
to really show
some very tight examples because this
paper is largely qualitative
but we're now trying to show some very
specific examples
where you where we can we can actually
track the scaling so so you have lower
level subunits so let's say you have
cells
that have only local metabolical so all
they know how to do is pursue some some
energy level in a kind of homeostasis to
stay alive
and so the question is how do you
connect those in a way
that is then going to give rise to a
larger agent that has much larger scale
goals that can be
uh working towards a a state of affairs
and
and to be actually stressed by the
failure to reach a state of affairs
that is way bigger than any individual
cell and so
i'm not sure that there's any kind of
conservation here in the sense that
there's only a total amount that you
sort of have to partition it among the
levels and
and that's all that there is i'm i'm not
sure that's yeah i would i would make
that claim i think that
um the total amount of individuality can
change over time and it can rise and
fall and in fact the boundaries between
the different
agents can can grow and shrink that's a
that was a significant part of the paper
to talk about that
um and what there's a couple of there's
a couple of interesting things that get
passed upwards so to speak um definitely
a kind of force graining in the sense
that
if you are a system whose parts are
themselves competent in getting various
things done despite changing conditions
and and so on they're not just the
hard-wired mechanisms but actually
competent to pursue specific outcomes
despite perturbations
what it means is that the larger system
is now
working in a much easier space in the
sense that
it's if it doesn't have to micromanage
all the micro states
that that the individual pieces are
doing but it can rely on those
components to get there to get their job
done then what you're really
working in is a much is a much lower
dimensional simpler space
where problem solving gets easier and
just as a simple biological example
you know we now know that uh for example
in the in the tadpole if you uh
if you activate uh a signal that
triggers it happens to be a bioelectric
signal that that triggers
eye formation in another part of the
embryo let's say on the tail
then all kinds of interesting things
will happen
it will it will build an eye it will
recruit cells that you never directly
manipulated so it's a local
self-organization process
that eye will form even though it's
sitting in the middle of muscle instead
of
in the brain where it where it belongs
all these things are going to happen
anyway
if you're if you're at the larger and by
the way those tackles can then see out
of that eye even though it's on the tail
instead of
in the head so if you are a system that
um needs to solve some problems in terms
of
uh i've got some eyes and i need to do
this behavior that i'm doing and so on
if you don't have to micromanage all of
those components
and saying each cell of that eye where
exactly it's going to go what exactly
it's going to attach to and so on
if if there is an effector that you have
access to an affordance
maybe that says build an eye and you as
a larger system don't need to know how
that's going to happen you can just
trust that that is going to happen under
a wide range of conditions you have a
much simpler
space to work in and the problem solving
that's one of the things we're doing now
is trying to map out some of the
different
spaces in which all these different
agents are actually solving problems
and trying to define what that what that
means uh
so one of the things that that gets that
gets passed up is this is is this uh
coarse graining because of the lower
level competency so that that's
i think a key thing and maybe we'll get
to talking about what that does for
evolution because i think it's massively
important
nice sarah i don't have a unfortunately
they've moved to change the interface so
i don't know where the hand is anymore
in this but
um one question that keeps coming up for
me in in all the different
um realms of discussion about this is
like well in particular with the
bioelectricity part you know you you use
the word
um subroutines when you were talking
about you know we we think we're
starting to understand the
the the whatever combinatorics of of how
this works and
and and also related to these nested
levels and things like this
i i just keep wondering if it's your
sense
from all of this work that you've done
that in nature
in in in the communication between these
levels
that there's any amount of abstraction
or semantic layer that's needed um
for for that to happen uh between
uh levels you know and also with the
electricity like subroutine implies that
there's some kind of semantics
um that something has to rest on and i
that just keeps coming back to me do you
have any sense about that
yeah so so a couple of things so one
thing about bioelectricity
is that um bioelectricity i
i think is interesting not because it's
in some sense uh you know magical or
there's some there's
something you know sort of uniquely
better about bioelectricity than
biomechanical or biochemical um modes
of interaction what i think is really
interesting about bioelectricity is that
that is what is being used and perhaps
these other modes too
are too we don't know but but
bioelectricity for sure
is uh being used as the
computational medium by which the lower
levels um bind together into the higher
level cognition
so so about the higher systems cognition
whatever
level it may have so what the
bioelectricity allows us to do is to
directly peek
into that computation and so i think
that's why it's interesting
um which is no surprise that's exactly
when people do neural decoding that's
exactly what they hope right is that by
tracking the bioelectricity
they learn something about the
information content of the global system
right what is the
the animal or the or the human thinking
about so it's exactly the same here so
that that's what's unique about
bioelectricity and i think that
uh what evolution discovered very early
on
is that and and and then it capitalized
on that by pivoting it into
into neural kinds of systems and we do
it in our computational devices and so
on
is that what evolution found really
really early
is around the time of bacterial biofilms
actually is that
electricity is a great way to process
information to integrate information
across distance
and to do computations right now that
shouldn't be a surprise to anybody
so um i don't know if i would claim that
it has
uh you know any kind of a formal syntax
at these levels or anything like that
but what it definitely does do is a kind
of
when i say subroutine what i'm mostly
leaning on is
this idea of modularity but not just
modularity in form because that's been
discussed a lot in evolutionary
developmental biology but
actually modularity of function so so
the key the the thing the thing about a
good subroutine
is that you're going to when you
activate the subroutine
you can move along and assume that
everything that's necessary to get that
job done
given whatever local conditions or
current events whatever else is
happening
that subroutine is going to encapsulate
everything that's needed to get it done
meaning it's
it's it's not just it's it's it's the
difference basically so for people who
code it's the difference between
sort of macro substitution where all
you're doing is
just you know it's a shorthand for a
bunch of hardwired steps which is
plopping that in i don't think that's
the the magic here at all i think what
it is is
is uh it's a degree of competency in
that subroutine to get something
accomplished
and and that that has really uh
really important implications for
evolvability and so on and
what the bioelectricity allows you to do
is to
uh basically to have um to have a
language
in which the system can call up such
such
circuits with specific behaviors um at
different points or at
different times that makes it that makes
it really really powerful
but um the question of whether it has
you know any kind of uh
formal syntax or anything like that i
don't have good evidence for that
i don't even mean like a formal syntax
it's it's almost like
it and and this also you know holds true
between these layers of these nested
layers of
organism or whatever um is is
if there's if you have a sense that
there's any abstraction there's any
abstraction layer needed
and i guess you kind of answered it
maybe by saying you know that
electricity is this medium
on which um things communicate or
but yeah anyway that it's i don't think
it's an easy it's like
you know easy to answer question but
that's the theme that keeps coming back
to me so
i i think there's a lot of abstraction
in the sense of
in and and i don't know if this captures
what you're asking but but there's a lot
of abstraction
in the sense of generalization um
in terms of um
another way to another way to say is is
is is corresponding
voltage itself let's just start with
that voltage itself is an abstraction
for cells because
and in fact people will often ask if i
say you know there's a bioelectrical
signal
they say well is it the potassium level
is it the sodium level
like what you know is it the particular
ion channel gene
is the voltage or is it the current yeah
yeah and in particular with so so the
cool thing about bioelectrics is that
with that question has been answered and
we know we know the answer
it's it's neither of those things so so
it's a pattern of voltage that is
specific for the downstream effects and
it doesn't matter how with very rare
exceptions it doesn't matter how you got
to that voltage so you can use sodium
channels you can use potassium channels
chloride
what ion used all those micro details
don't matter at all because what the
collective is keying off of
is the spatial temporal distribution of
voltage and you can get exactly the same
results with sodium or potassium or
chloride as long as you're
you know you're you're driving the right
voltage patterns so voltage itself is a
really cool abstraction because
it means that all the downs the
underlying mechanisms are free to
diverge in evolution you want to swap
out a potassium channel
for sodium channel you can do that as
long as uh you've got the right of
functional properties so that your
you know your overall pattern stays and
we use that quite often in our
regenerative medicine applications with
a really convenient um
convenient property so so yeah so so the
bioelectric code itself is definitely an
abstraction
over uh what the microstates in terms of
specific
ions or the specific channel genes that
got you there
nice stephen did you want to say hello
yes hello hello hi there i'm michael
thanks for joining us yeah i was curious
we had a really interest
chris field gave us a really good
insight into the quantum contextuality
idea of how things could build up from
different sort of space states at very
small levels and active inference often
uses non-equilibrium
steady steady-state attractors as kind
of a way to look at
some sort of statistics between the
scales you know there's some sort of
flux or um flow that's inferred
and i i find it really useful
thinking about it with this cone idea
that you you bring to the table because
it
it there's more it's more of an idea of
a distinct um swarming going into a
structure
and some sort of system that might
emerge from that which is sometimes
lost when it's very much in the math um
and i'm curious um whether when you
think about these
um the bi-electric effects and the same
sort of question came up with quantum
contextuality maybe is
is is there more of a distinct scale at
which
there's a coherence you know like you've
got the cell membrane then you've got a
coherence
around which the bioelectrics can
operate so to speak and then you might
have another distinct level at which
um the bioelectrics can operate
which is maybe more than the more
gradated idea
of steady state statistical um
sort of manifolds so i was wondering
what your thoughts are about how
and where there's sort of scales at
which
the bioelectrics become particularly um
coherent or if that even happens
yeah i mean so so again prefacing this
by saying that
the the bioelectrics is not an essential
part of the story
in except in so far as i think
morphogenesis
and is is a nice example of an
unconventional agent within which to uh
play with these kind of ideas you know
what so so what i would like to do and
and this is um a framework that i've
been
developing recently is to get away from
the standard
sorts of living creatures that we're
used to right so so the products of
that one trace of evolution in the in
the biosphere on earth
and to go beyond that and to look at the
space of possible agents the space of
possible bodies and the space of
possible minds that
those bodies will support and think you
know think more broadly so
in in in doing that um what i think the
bioelectrics in morphogenetic
well i think that morphogenesis is a
nice example of an
unconventional agent that lets us see
how the framework is to be practically
applied
right so so people say okay this is all
well and good but what what you know
what use is it
okay let's let's apply it to a specific
thing then
really no one thinks of as a as a
cognitive agent i'm going to show you
how all this stuff
maps and why it's useful at the bench
and it helps do new experiments and so
on
so if we if we accept that morphogenesis
is kind of a test case
for and there are many others it's
certainly not unique but it's a test
case for
an unconventional place to find um
agency and all of that and to test out
how well this theory helps us out
then what's cool about bioelectricity is
that it actually
allows us to tell a very specific
mechanistic testable
empirically useful story about how the
information
flow happens and how the levels scale
but it's just
one you know it's just that that's just
happens to be how the morphogenetic
um self does things and there are plenty
of other interesting
you know cells that wouldn't have
anything to do with bioelectricity i
just want to make that make that clear
right the bioelectricity is not
so you know some sort of essential um
element that's always going to be
present whenever we apply these things
it's just
sort of it's central to this to the to
the example case that i've trotted out
which is which is morphogenesis
now having said that bioelectricity is
definitely multi-scale because you have
uh you have you have bioelectric
dynamics in organelles in a very small
scale
you have uh the resting potential across
the cell membrane which is
mainly what what we study but those
scale into tissues
and you have global electrical fields
which are driven by trans epithelial
potentials
on the scale of tissues and organs which
other people like mensau and many other
people
study and then past that you have whole
animal
scale like whole body scale uh fields as
well
so all of these different levels you
know exist
uh some of them more and some less rely
on bioelectricity but
um yeah it's it's it's relevant in this
particular unconventional agent it's
it's relevant to all the scales that we
as we know
okay that that's really helpful thanks
and and would you say that the the cone
concept could have extrapolated to other
types of multi-scale piston blanket
type ideas um and i just wonder what
your thoughts on that or whether that
just confuses things
to try that but um no i don't think it
confuses now i should
i'll i'll i'll say i'm i'm for sure not
i mean i i like
uh carl's ideas very much i'm by no
means an expert on the map and i'm not
gonna pretend that i understand all that
but um i i think that the the thing
about the thing about these kind of
diagrams is they're not to be
they're not meant to be unique or
exhaustive
so with the goal of this originally this
this came about
um a couple years ago um at a templeton
meeting where
we were asked to brainstorm ways to
define almost a sort of ident space
where you're you're able to compare
directly
really diverse intelligences right so so
things where you don't
you can't just uh measure all their
brains and then see how they you know
how they shake out it's it's
really really diverse intelligence and
so it's what i tried to come up with
is uh a scale and and it's all focused
around uh the the spatial temporal scale
of the goals that any given
agent can work towards and and the scale
of
um states of affairs that can be that
can stress out that agent when they're
not being met and so on
uh as a way to uh pick on something that
i think is central to all ages no matter
what they're made of no matter how they
got here evolve design
combinations chimeras whatever wherever
they came from and whatever they are
what is essential to them and and i
picked this this goal directing this but
but this is compatible with all kinds of
other systems
so you could overlay on top of this
almost
anything else that you thought was
critical about being an agent
just start adding dimensions you know
and and and absolutely
right now you can you can just you can
this this is compatible with all sorts
of things this is not meant
to rule out any other anybody else's you
know favorite and favorite framework
they're saying it captures one slice of
what's essential about being a self
thanks that's really useful actually can
i just one more thing blue i just
was i'm actually really interested in
this i do a lot of work with community
psychology
um so there's this challenge of going
from the cell there's like the self and
then there's
society social but the inter-subjective
kind of group dynamics is there's a big
problem because it's like a big hole
because it and and this i find it's
really useful because
a lot of stuff which talks about how
groups they often try to project out
into the future as if it's a light
beam that you could measure whereas here
it's much more you know like
it's sitting in the swarming i like to
think the bottom of the cone is almost
the swarming
dynamics that go down into the past
you've got the kind of structure of the
cell that's emerged
and then the system that's able to go
into
temporal depth in the future in the code
and i think that
that offers a nice way to think about
group dynamics particularly maybe the
more di
ironically the more challenging group
dynamics where there isn't a coherent
single narrative so there might be
applications there
yeah this is this is so super
interesting and i should i should say
one of the things about the cone and we
had a discussion about this yesterday
um and pranav das pointed out that my
cone compared to
minkowski's coin is upside down right
it's it's uh and the reason i did it
this way
was because if you think about
um where where any any given agent the
only thing
the given agent is really certain of at
the
at the moment is what's going on right
now
so your future obviously is is uncertain
and when you're trying to predict so so
let's say you're trying to manage goals
and
and you're trying to predict you've got
some predictive capacity going forward
that predictive
capacity doesn't get better over time it
gets worse over time right
you're you're you're sort of
exponentially more uncertain about
what's going to happen later on so your
ability to pursue those goals in the
future
get smaller and smaller same thing goes
back in the past although you could
argue that that's linear and not
exponential
but again what you're doing at any given
moment in time
is inferring what your past was from the
engrams of memory that are available to
you they may be a brain they might be a
stigmatic a medium that you live in on
the you know within if you're in a
company colony whatever it's going to be
you've got some kind of material in
which
you leave me in which in which events
leave memories they leave traces
at any given moment you are reading
those traces recalling them and
reconstructing
what you think the past was that's your
only evidence for what the past
you know any given moment what actually
and so
and so you and so and so even going
backwards my cone comes down because
your ability to um to go backwards in
time and be certain of what went on and
when what are
what are the facts on which you can now
build your goal directed strategy going
forward
become more and more uncertain going
back so so that's that's why my you know
my cones are
are upside down in this in the so to
speak because also because there's no
particular reason this has to map
exactly onto you know minkowski's
informalism but but i think it's close
that just because that that
that your your level of certainty is
highest right now right both in space
and time and anything
when you step away from that it rapidly
you know at least for all of us
rapidly um get smaller
yeah we were really actually talking
about this last week in our
discussion and we were kind of thinking
about this as like an information cone
because you have the most information
about your environment at this
point in space and less information as
you go forward and backward
in time so do you think that that might
be the
the correct way to think about it so so
that's true it's def
that's absolutely true it's definitely
also an information point but i want to
be clear about this because
um this diagram is not a diagram of
what you can sense or how far your
effectors range
this is which this is um the the the
what you just said about the information
certainty
is uh the the consequences of that are
that you also have a limited cone in
what the diagram really is supposed to
show
which is the scale of the goals towards
which you can work
so so because the information is smaller
your ability to pursue goals towards you
know how far into the future are
am i actively you know doing it just it
just becomes limited
right your your ability to do so so it's
sort of a secondary um
a consequence of that but but i just
want to be clear that this is this is
not meant to be fundamentally a picture
of
the information certainty of sensory
capacity of
um effector range or anything like that
this is this is a diagram
in um in gold space
nice so one of the other ways i've been
thinking about it is kind of like a
possibility cone
so like as you progress forward into the
future we all
are left with one possibility and that's
like death right so your
goal at that moment is death um and
similarly in the past like we all come
from a single
celled like you know fertilization event
and so like we all started an event and
ended an event and like the maximum
possibility is
is now so what do you think about that
yeah i mean so so that's a really
interesting point right and people talk
about
you know great transitions in uh in in
cognition along the continuum and so on
and so i think one great cognition of a
great transition is the following
if you are a creature with a horizon
with a with a with a
cognitive horizon of you know a half an
hour your goldfish or something i don't
know if this is factually true but you
know you're some you're
some sort of um form that has a
cognitive horizon of a half an hour
right
what that means is that all of your uh
major goals survival and these other
things they're totally achievable
right because it is completely plausible
that you are going to make it for that
half hour that you can project forward
if you are a human and your cognitive
horizon your your goals
are you know i don't know world peace or
your buildings you know
the larger things you are for the first
time perhaps along
the earth's lineage anyway you are able
to to
to uh comprehend goals that you have no
chance whatsoever of achieving
because you because you because you have
a limited lifespan so now that's and
that's a that's a really sharp um
transition you know kind of an emergent
transition because for the first time
you are able to undertake goals that you
know you are not going to complete
guarantee
right whereas the fish essence you know
maybe you'll get eaten and maybe you
won't but it's totally plausible that
you you know that you live for the half
hour that you can see forward for the
very humans have that and so i suspect
that this is uh and this is you know
sort of way above my opinion to know
details about this but
but i suspect this drives a lot of um
the weird facts about human psychology
because you now have this fundamental
stressor
that other creatures don't have because
you're able to foresee all these goals
that you are definitely not going to
to meet and and that's that's a novel
you know sort of
um a conflict between the different
modules that
that doesn't exist doesn't exist for i
think for most other creatures
yeah that's really interesting you know
something that i might be like uniquely
human
is like this possibility to see past
like the cone of our own existence like
into the future
uh with these like future possibilities
or future goal states and also like
backwards into the past in like a
historical sense so we all like look at
history
um so i don't know i like thinking about
like you know i've just been reading
your recent paper this
integrating evolutionary developmental
thinking into scale free biology this
paper with chris fields
um and i know like when we spoke
yesterday you mentioned you were
integrating these ideas maybe into your
next paper but
in that paper you guys were kind of
blurring the boundary really between
the processes of evolution and
development
and you know phylogenetic memory that's
contained in dna
and results from evolution like
transforms into this onto
genetic yeah yeah definitely so so
there's a couple of really interesting
things
related to that to evolution that we
that we can talk about and that's that's
something i'm working on now and this
thing should be done then
in a couple of weeks and then we'll see
um
two things number one um one of the
things
but one of the amazing things about
biological hardware that that's given to
us by evolution
is that it is there's a default
way by that i mean cells but they're
genomically determined
proteins whatever they have uh there's a
default and a pretty con
robust consistent default outcome right
and and so so embryo you know fish
embryos make fish and progress make
frogs and so on
but there's an incredible amount of
plasticity there so that those
exact same cells genetically wild type
so the hardware is all the same
are in fact in other types of
environments are able to make
completely novel um
creatures right and so some of this so
synthetic synthetic biology and
synthetic morphology is already showing
this we we
you know as our zenobots and things like
this and then there will be tons more
going forward that what's interest one
thing that's interesting about those
novel creatures
is that you don't have a long history
of uh select specific selection and
frozen accidents and all this you know
phylogenetics
to uh lean on when you ask why do they
do certain things
right so for every normal animal in the
in the biosphere you say why is this
thing
you know green and why does it fly and
how come it has these antennas the
answer is always the same well because
for millions of years the ancestors were
selected for this event
the fact that we can take those embryos
those cells rather
cell cells from from from those kind of
animals and put them together
into a new creature that has goals
and behaviors more morphological goals
behavioral goals physiological goals
that basically appear overnight you know
within
24 48 hours they sort of show up
um and then the then the question is
where did these things come from because
what they didn't do
was uh to be honed over millions of
years by specific selection pressure so
so that that's a very interesting to me
to me aspect of the plasticity here that
it is not you know they the history
doesn't necessarily
determine them other than
the default you know sort of variant and
where does that come from and then
there's a whole thing which you know i
don't know you can tell me if you want
to
dive deeper into this or not but the
whole um
the fact that you have multiple layers
and that you have competency going down
you know sort of all the way down has
massive implications for
why evolution works so fast right why
why actually anything
is able to evolve on the on the time
scale that we see so i think
you know if you're interested we can get
into that yeah that's great why don't we
uh unpack that
okay um yeah let's let's let's talk
about that a little bit um
imagine imagine two kinds of creatures
and uh you've got one kind of creature
where the genome has a pretty direct
um influence over what the anatomy is
going to be it's
everything is hardwired in some in some
sense and so let's say
let's let's let's visualize you've got
let's let's say it's a you know it's a
frog of some kind
and uh and and and there's the genome
and it makes a frog and that's what it
does and so now
now we imagine evolution is sort of
searching the space and now there's a
mutation
and the mutation does two things uh
because most mutations do multiple
things let's say we got a mutation that
there's two things it it moves the eyes
off kilter right and it also
has some really beneficial uh effect
somewhere else you know it helps with
some other things
most mutations are clear tropics so it's
it's um it's a reasonable
reasonable conjecture if you're if your
animal is
uh the hardwired kind the eyes are in
the wrong place nothing works
you the evolution never gets to explore
the positive benefits of this other
mutation
because the thing's going to be dead you
know it's just it's just not a workable
animal anymore the fitness is very low
it's gone and so most when if you think
about these kind of hardwired things
it's the same when i when i first you
know now 100 years ago when i first
heard about
how evolutionary algorithms are supposed
to work this idea that i've got a system
that does something i'm going to start
throwing random changes in
anybody that's written any code that
they are you crazy of course
everything's going to get worse not
better that's never going to work
now imagine imagine a different now of
course it works but it takes it takes
massive amounts of time and
and so and there's all these
difficulties about evolving complex
things
now imagine what we actually have the
actual and i'll explain the the
biological um example that's when you
have
you have a tadpole and the temple has to
move all of its uh
oregon's craniofacial organs around to
become a fraud so the jaws have to come
out the nostrils move the eyes move
forward like everything all this stuff
moves around and
you could have a hard-wired animal in
which every
every organ moves in the right direction
a particular a distance and that's it
right and that that's you that's your
hard-wired thing that actually is not
what um how animals work so so if we and
so what we did a few years ago is we
make what we call these picasso tadpoles
the idea is you make these tadpoles
everything's in the wrong place the eyes
are on the back of the head the mouth is
off to the side the nostrils are up here
like it's just scratched
like mr potato everything's scrambled so
if it was a hard-wired
system then all of these things would
move the traditional amount in the
traditional direction
and everything would be way off because
you're starting in the wrong spot
instead what happens is that all of
these organs move in novel paths
and they keep moving and sometimes they
overshoot and have to come back
but they keep moving until they build a
correct frog face and then they stop
moving
so now that system so so what the
genetics actually gives you it doesn't
it doesn't somehow give you a hard-wired
set of movements what it does do
is give you an error minimization scheme
that
can progressively uh deform the system
uh until the error from some sort of set
point and we've been
studying you know what the set point is
we can talk about that uh
until the error with from that set point
gets to an acceptably low level
so what you have here is a competent set
of craniofacial organs
that are going to move around and and
get to where they need to go
even if they start off in the wrong
position so now look at what happens
with evolution right you got your
mutation
the the eyes and the jaws now are off in
the wrong place
but now you've got this benefit
somewhere else the the thing is the eyes
and the jaws are going to get fixed
you don't need to worry about that
because they're going to they know where
they belong they're going to get there
even though they start out in the wrong
position so that aspect
that negative aspect of that mutation
gets hidden
from selection for a while anyway
because um and eventually it'll it'll
you know it'll catalyze into into the
genome itself but but for a while
it gets hidden from selection allowing
evolution to explore
the benefits of of the other benefits of
that mutation
so so here's all in summary here's
here's what this means the fact that you
have competent subunits and they're
competent morphologically they're
competent physiologically we can talk
about what that means
the fact that they're all competent
means that the uh the fitness landscape
is
is much less rugged it's much it's much
smoother
it means that uh your um the effects of
mutations are much more linear
meaning that you can you can examine
each consequence
uh independently because the other
consequences can be masked by
by things you know if by the local
environment being off it doesn't matter
it'll things still get where they need
to go and connect and so on
so so it makes it makes the search
process way more easier by
uh by allowing you to and it gives you
patience it means that
evolution doesn't have to solve every
problem at once you don't have to wait
until you find a mutation that
gives you a positive impact and leaves
the eyes where they need to be
you don't need to wait for that if you
can you can grab the first mutation you
find that gives you the positive impact
because the i think will get taken care
of because because those subunits are
confident
so it's what raises the iq of the whole
system the search becomes a much
much smarter search it has it has some
patience it's able to see linearly
instead of um sort of highly uh
um you know mixed up uh
all of the consequences of these
mutations and it smooths the fitness
landscape
so i think when you can count on your uh
your components to do some of the heavy
lifting you don't have to micromanage
all of it
uh the evolutionary search gets
massively more efficient
and now it because it starts to become a
little more plausible
that we actually see this you know this
amazing biosphere
actually evolved by a process of random
mutation
nice so in that same paper you talk
about random mutation but then you
also describe this kind of modularity of
gene groups and the possibility of
entire gene families
like the hox cluster duplicating and
driving the major evolutionary
transitions
is this a sort of non-random process
sort of ergodicity
breaking with perhaps like non-linear
effects when these entire clusters
yeah i i hesitate to say too much
because i don't think much is known
there that i can say definitively i
think that you know this whole issue of
random and non-random mutations is very
um you know controversial obviously i
suspect
that there is a notion of mutate of of
evolutionary search that's not quite
blind
so so people often will argue you know
either they
most people nowadays evolution is
completely blind you know it just
that makes these mutations whatever
happens is not because of any
uh directionality in the search space
and then and then you know you've got
you've got you have people who think
that it's directed towards a specific
outcome i
i think there's a there's a sort of
in-between scenario where
it's definitely not directed in the
sense that you can see
far forward in the search space but it
doesn't have to be completely blind
in that maybe what it has this comes out
of some discussions i've had with both
chris fields and richard watson that
that maybe instead of a point
in fitness space what you really have is
a little bit of a vector you have
almost like a comet trail right and then
it gives you a little bit of um
a little bit of information about
direction about you know and
and and and you can imagine i mean i can
sort of design in my head
an epigenetic system of marking things
on the dna that
give you a little bit of about
information well what was this allele
last time
right so that you can sort of say well
i've been turning i've been turning this
knob in this direction and things are
going well so maybe i want to turn it
some more
that kind of thing and this is totally
made up i'm not saying that that we know
that biology actually does this it's
just
maybe it doesn't then maybe synthetic
biology maybe we implement this on you
know just for the first time we engineer
it
but i think it's possible to make a
system that does that and maybe
um collections of genes and some of the
complex chromatin
um epigenetics that go on maybe they're
part of that process but this is this is
total
conjecture at this point so sarah i know
you have a question but i'm going to use
my moderator's privilege here and just
ask do you think that this vector-driven
mutation could be perhaps driven by
active inference some kind of vector
between
exploration and exploitation happening
yeah and so and so one of the things
that that we've
we talked about i mean that i'm to write
after this next
thing is out is is is really on this
idea that maybe
um the whole evolutionary evolutionary
lineage of a particular
um of you know particular um
the animal plant or whatever it is uh
maybe that's the
maybe that's an agent as well just
stretched out massively over space
such that each at any given point in
time all of the off
all of the existing uh uh um examples of
that species
are in fact hypotheses about the space
right and that what you're doing what
that what you're doing is
is you're constantly generating genomes
as
as hypotheses and some of those genomes
are
you know proven to be some of those
hypotheses are proven good and some are
not
and then the next you know sort of the
next set of genomes is not completely
random
but it's in some way uh part of this
part of the
um active inference of this giant is
sort of
you know virtual agent right so i think
there's a story to be told like that
uh but it's way more hand waving than
details at this point
awesome thanks sarah yeah my comment is
now maybe a little bit stale but i think
i'll put it out there anyway just for
the sake of making
saying something concrete because a lot
of this feels a bit abstract like
um and i'm hoping i'm even remembering
this anecdote right but i remember
uh learning that some gene once upon a
time
um that gave us um
an extra writer cone in our eye allowed
us better color reception
also was the same gene that um shut off
our ability to make our own vitamin c
and um if that's correct if i'm
remembering that correct that's such an
interesting example of
of yeah of course it's an example of the
of the fact that genes do multiple
things but but it was kind of like isn't
that coincidental you know that
that this um
that that gene is is doing you know both
something for the eye but then
also making it so that you can get your
own vitamin c you know by
by looking at fruit and i just thought
that was that that kept coming to me as
an example of what you guys were talking
about
um but it's stale sort of thanks sarah
i'm sorry for
making your comments still uh stephen
yeah sort of following on it's this
you have this idea of like um a goal
space or a tedeological space in a way
that's really interesting and then with
that exploit
or explore you i wonder if there's a
time when
there's there's a thought about when
things are
very directed and of course our western
thinking we tend to think about a nice
pointed cone
um where we go into the future and we
because we sculpt the world around us
we maybe have like a a distinctive
trajectory
because we we kind of we're constructing
our world
more and more which is probably part of
our problem to make it the way we want
it to be
um whereas particularly if you look at
indigenous cultures they would have
you know a cyclical the more cyclical
approach which would go
through seven generations or different
levels of generations and would be
attuning
to the environment and i'm kind of
curious whether and again this might be
where we don't really know but
is there a point at which there's
generally trying to come back
uh or maintain in the allostasis
the kind of the cyclical sort of pattern
that is where we want to go to and is
there a time when it's like okay we're
we're branching out now like we've made
a jump and we're going to try and
inscribe our environment at different
scales from the body out
to sort of now maintain some new
kind of steady state attractor and how
that might fit with this
yeah i mean i think i i i think you're
absolutely right in that some
future version of this is going to have
to
uh be able to deal with goals that are
not only not static meaning they're
cyclical
but also um
goals that are themselves you know let's
say second order
goals like like my goal is it's a
derivative
my goal is to get better at something
it's not a particular level that i'm
looking for
but i want a particular slope of some
variable being
you know particular right so something
like that so so
you're absolutely right i started out
with the simplest you know this is sort
of the hydrogen atom of this thing so i
started out with something very simple
that it's homeostatic
as in your your goal is a is to achieve
a particular region in whatever space
you're solving problems and be that
morphe space or
physiological space your goal is to find
that region and sit there
and and that of course is not all there
is to life obviously that's just the
first you know kind of stuff
i just did that for simplicity because i
want to tackle everything at once and
and there needs to be a lot done here
before we get to that point
um but yeah you're absolutely right your
your goal state in that space may not be
a point it may be some interesting
you know bigger bigger bigger shape you
know and this thing and and i just want
to i wanted to say something about
these gold spaces because i think it's
it's it's interesting to to point this
out
so um one of the
in this in this this all came out of a
meeting on diverse intelligences and and
so one thing i've been thinking about is
what
what is intelligence and you know what
are these agents actually trying to do
and okay so so we have lots of examples
of problem solving in three-dimensional
space right so you've got
you know pros and monkeys and everything
else and they're running around and
trying to solve
problems by moving around in
three-dimensional space but but
all the different um subunits of the of
of bodies
are solving problems in other kinds of
spaces so we talked about amorphous
space
so if you are an eye in the head of a
frog
you are working in a space of possible
configurations of where you are relative
to everything else
and you are trying to move and and act
in a way that is going to
to um to acquire to a particular region
of amorphous space that describes
that that the correct frog head that's
that's where you're trying to land
there's also a physiological space so
i'll just give you a simple example
that's that
that we found recently so so um these
these flat worms these
planaria uh you you take these planaria
and you throw them in barium okay so a
solution of bearing
now uh what happens is the barium is a
non-selective potassium channel blocker
it it blocks all the potassium channels
all the cells freak out their head
their heads literally explode right over
overnight you know their heads just
degenerate
they're gone if you take those planaria
and you leave them
in fresh barium over
the next you know 10 20 days what they
will do is they will build
new heads that are completely barium and
sensitive
couldn't care less no problem at all
they live in barrie which is fine so
we we we asked the simple question and
not not because the answer has to be
this but just because that's the tool
that
that was available we asked the simple
question what is transcriptionally
different about barium adapted heads
from normal heads
right so what genes are different
differently expressed in
in these in these heads and so what you
find out is that
out of tens of thousands of genes that
these planaria have
they managed to regulate a very small
number on the order of of a couple dozen
that allow them now to do their business
despite the fact that potassium is no
longer
usable for them so now this is
incredible because think about the
problem that they're solving i
you know my head i always visualize like
one of those nuclear reactor control
rooms with buttons everywhere
so each button is a different gene you
can you what are you going to do you
have a physiological stressor
you can't pass potassium everything's
everything's going to happen
you have some tens of thousands of genes
that you could turn on and off
the combinatorics are astronomical you
don't have time
to try them all you don't even have time
for gradient descent
you don't reproduce fast enough it's not
like bacteria where you could say well
they're all random and then somebody
will survive and repopulate ahead they
don't they don't divide that fast
so you don't have time for any kind of
evolutionary explanation within
some small number of days you have to
home in on
a small number of genes knowing that if
you just start randomly flipping them up
and down you're going to make things
worse long before you make them better
you're going to kill everything off you
just randomly start
so now the other important fact about
this is that um planaria never
see barium in the wild so so planaria
there's no evolutionary history of being
good at
surviving in barium because they don't
see bearing so now
to me this is an amazing example of of
problem solving in a high dimensional
virtual space you've got this
you've got this um physiological space
and your problem is your your your
problem is physiological
your effectors are transcriptional
largely of course you have physiological
effects too but you're trying to walk in
this
in this space and you have to somehow
map
it's unbelievable how they do this you
somehow have to map your effectors in in
transcriptional space
to what's happening to you in
physiological space and then rapidly get
to
a a workable uh a workable region
so so that that gives you an idea of
what of what we're talking about right
these spaces can be
um transcriptional physiological all you
know all
all kinds um and and these things and
they solve their problems and like
and like you pointed out the correct the
thing you're trying to achieve may not
be a point
is certainly not a point and let's face
it but it may not even be a static area
it may be some sort of
i would like to sort of wander in this
you know kind of weird loop that's
that's my goal right is to
you know it's just to wander in some
sort of weirdly shaped attractor yeah
well we'll get to that this is the just
you know first step
just just one just also just just just
one question following up from that just
before sarah um
so if i'm right what you're saying is
gradient descent because that would have
to come
so from where you are and slowly keep
incrementing you
there's somehow some there's some goal
states i mean
maybe there's some evolutionary history
even if it's not barium something like
barium
but but somehow it's not it's not only
going
from adjacent possibilities
it's it's somehow jumping ahead is that
what you're saying
so so the first thing i'm saying is that
i don't have any idea how it works right
so so i do not i am not claiming i have
a good
a model for what's going on here but but
i think you're on to something which is
that
i think and i think we talked about this
a few minutes ago which was
um abstraction and generalization i
think you're exactly right i think what
the system is able to do
is is to say okay i don't know what this
barium is but i've been terribly
depolarized before it was an epileptic
you know kind of a thing and this is an
awful lot like that so
i'm gonna generalize what just happened
to this other thing that i do know how
to deal with
right and i'm going to move in that
direction so that's my that's my gut
feeling i don't have a solid model for
this and
that's not been proven in any way um but
i have a feeling that you're that that's
where the answer is going to be it's
going to be
that each and that that it's able to do
this because it is able to recognize
this
physiological problem as an instance of
a larger class of things for which it
does know how to do
and i think that when we talk about
intelligence for all of these agents
what we're really saying is
it's your ability to navigate these
various spaces uh if
efficiently and without getting trapped
in local minima that they kill you right
being
being able to step temporarily you know
it's that patience it's that
it's that being able to step away from
the direct line to your goal to then
come around and
um and get i have sometimes when i talk
about this i have a picture of this
there's a fence and there's a couple of
dogs on either side of the fence and
they're just like you know trying to get
at each other right
there's a hole in the fence four feet
away so they could do it
the problem is it temporarily requires
you to get away from get further from
your goal right
so that ability you're trapped in this
local local local maximum
and um your intelligence is is directly
uh sort of proportional to your ability
to temporarily
get further from your goal in order to
actually get into a better position
later on
part of the iq but i think the other
part of the iq is this kind of
generalization
right and i and i think you're right i
think that's probably what is gonna end
up explaining
nice sarah um man this is great
uh i this is this question is probably
out of bounds but if you have any
thoughts on it
then great if not pass um i mean this uh
the the cone type diagram and the
the agential um helios that it assumes
i'm just wondering if you feel
like there's any applicability to to
non-agential
type phenomena like you know complex
systems or hurricanes or whatever um
because
it just when we're talking about
abstraction
um yeah i'm just wondering if if you
have any thoughts about
where that could go if anywhere yeah so
so the thing i'll say about that and i'm
sure
this is this is uh not uh you know this
is the kind of thing that's um
probably uh not not not a lot of people
will agree with this bit but this is my
view i to say non-agential
presupposes that you can draw a binary
sharp line
right and between things that are agents
and things that are not
i don't really believe in that i think
that's a
view that gets us into a lot of trouble
by looking at these support looking for
these sharp lines
i think that all there is is a degree of
agency and i'm not sure we are we talked
about yesterday whether there's such a
thing as zero i i don't actually i'm not
even sure there's a zero but but
certainly there are
there are things that are very very sort
of
non you know very very low levels of
agency and
and things that are very high and
everything is a smooth continuum so now
then so so then then then the question
is okay so what do you do with
hurricanes and things like this
so i drew um and this will be this you
know in the next uh in the next
paper there's a thing there's a thing
that i call um it's an axis of
persuadability
it's it and it's it's so it's sort of
related to um dennis intentional scenes
in the following way
there's a there's a there's a continuum
and
for any given system so so my claim is
that it's an empirical problem you can't
say whether something is or is not an
agent lots of people do they'll say well
that's not image
i think you you can't say that um until
you've done the empirical work and the
empirical work looks like this
all the way the the question is this as
an engineer this is very
much an engineering perspective as an
engineer how much
work do you have to do uh what do you
need to know about the system
and what kind of work do you have to do
to be able to control
and predict its outcome so i'll just
give you a couple of examples
all the way on the left you have things
that are like mechanical clocks
so if you're dealing with a system
that's like a mechanical clock
you know you can put it on the left of
this of this diagram
because you are not going to uh reason
with it you are not going to
train it you're not going to be able to
punish it you're not going to be able to
rewrite
it it's it's you know goal states you
have to you have to know
how it works and you have to micromanage
the hardware and you have to make um
uh you have to rewire the the the
physics of it to get it to do something
else okay
then moving on from that you have
something like a thermostat and with a
thermostat you're also not going to
reason or punt it with it or punish it
but there is a separate set point and if
you want the room to be kept in a
different temperature
range you don't have to rewire the
thermostat you can change the set point
so as and this has massive implications
for regenerative medicine that we can we
can talk about
the way you relate to the system is is
quite a bit
different now after that you might get
to systems that have
preferences in the sense that you can
actually train them meaning
you can provide rewards and punishments
they will
change their behavior because what
you're doing is you're relying on them
to be a
kind of learning system they're able to
do associative learning so they
associate
certain things you've done to them with
us you know with things that they did
and they will
change their behavior so now this means
that we can now think of what this means
you know
humanity has been training animals
for i don't know ten thousand years
whatever uh with knowing nothing about
neuroscience
it means that you don't actually have to
know what's going on inside your system
you don't need that micro level
hardware information what you all you
need
is uh to to know that that animal that
that
uh system is actually a that it has that
level of agency that it's
susceptible to this kind of um
interaction
and how do you know you don't know until
you've tried so we have no idea so one
of the things
we're doing now with charles abramson
who's a behaviorist
scientist we're right we're actually
writing a how-to um
manual you know how-to uh paper
on if you are given some sort of weird a
new synthetic system how do you know
where along the
and there's actually has a bunch of a
bunch of experiments that you do to
figure out where
you are along this this path so you can
go further
and and there are other systems where
you know nothing about
um what's inside and in fact the amount
of energy that
it takes to manipulate them is tiny
because you can you can give them
reasons as opposed to causes
and you can you can give them
information and they will act on this
information and do various things
this is sophisticated um agents
so all that is to say uh the question of
where
something like a hurricane lands on this
on this on the spectrum
i think we need to really resist the
urge to just make pronouncements you
know sort of armchair pronouncements
about that
and we need to ask a simple question
which type of manipulation
is that system amenable to and when you
find out
then you know how much agency it has now
give you a simple example of
how this works we and other people have
done something similar
if you think about gene regulatory
networks so gene regulatory networks are
a
quintessential example of a you know
dynamical system it's it's
deterministic and all that and one of
the things we asked is we
we we simply said how do we know where
on this spectrum it lands let's just try
to train it
and see what happens and it turns out
and this is so we did this
computationally and now
we're sort of starting to do this at the
bench we simply ask the question could
gene regulatory networks have
associative learning capacity
and that means that you could do
interesting things you can do pavlov
dogs
experiment so you have a gene regulatory
network
you have some uh stimulus that causes it
to do something so you have your
unconditioned stimulus that causes the
response
you have this other thing that's a
that's a
neutral stimulus that normally doesn't
do anything uh
you pair presentations of the the
ucs and them and the neutral stimulus
together and after a while what you
might find
is that now take away the the original
unconditioned stimulus and use the
neutral stimulus and that's now enough
to trigger the response because there's
an associative memory that formed
in the network right so now we actually
tried this in the sense that we we took
a bunch of um
known gene regulatory networks from the
literature we made an algorithm that
basically checks for associative
learning and lo and behold we found two
things we found that
there are six different kinds of
memories that these things can do
including associated memories from any
of them and
that the biological networks have way
more memories than you find in random
random networks that you you know you
would just randomly concoct so
apparently
either directly or indirectly selection
likes that so that's just an example
of uh what you would do under this view
with with dynamical systems right that
that you would think oh you know these
are trouble cases are they agents or
aren't they
i think that's why we get in trouble
because we try to draw a sharp line i
think the answer is
there's somewhere on the line they could
be way over on the left or not
and you find out when you figure out
what kind of
intervention and strategy avails you of
the most predictive power with the least
amount of effort
nice so we talked yesterday kind of
about
um you know cells that are contiguous
and there's like connections and so this
this concept of like a shared
information making up
uh an individual or like what consists
like constitutes the boundary
you know if if cells are connected via
gap junctions and like
you talked about how if there's a
calcium molecule inside my cell
i don't know if it's from from me or
from my neighbor because we share this
kind of
hole between us and so i just wonder if
if there's some
degree of information sharing or some
kind of like proximal
like level does it have to be
immediately contiguous
to you know have that same like
cognitive capacity or
or like over a longer distance can this
also function
like for example if i get some kind of
like necrotizing
flesh in my leg is my toe
necessarily gonna know like what's going
on with my leg it's gonna take a while
for that signal to diffuse over such a
long distance so
so where is the like the boundary or
container space
for this kind of information sharing
that has to occur
to make this cognitive cognitive
individual
like a whole the whole thing by itself
so i don't know if you can say a little
bit more about that
yeah yeah um the biggest is so so i
think so i think one thing that i really
need to improve
in this whole thing for next time is a
better visualization and i
frankly don't yet know how to do it
because this this way of visualizing it
looks very
physical it looks like what the cone is
is it that the cone is at the edge of
the cells that are connected right it
sort of
gives this idea that what you're
measuring is the actual physical
boundary of the system
and that's not quite what i'm trying to
get across because
what what and and this is actually let's
just think about the cells
in in the in the um cancer versus
multicellularity right which is a nice
example of
how this works when you have a bunch of
cells
and they get together and they're going
to build a kidney
the um the size of
the at least the spatial size of that of
of that particular agent is going to be
roughly the size of the thing they're
working towards it's going to be the
size of that kidney right that's the
project they're all working on
um each individual cell has no idea what
a kidney is but the collective
intelligence of that group of cells
it has a uh a goal that's trying to
build my kidney if you try to deviate it
from that goal it will do its best to
get back and do it anyway
um so what you would be measuring there
is
the uh the size of the of the state that
it's trying to achieve not necessarily
this you know where the edges of the of
the now there's certainly some
relationship there because in this
particular example
what an a as you said what enables the
cells to work together is the fact that
they're electrically coupled into one
and chemically coupled into one giant
network so so there's some relationship
but it's not quite always the edge
right you know what i mean and and the
same thing with the individual cells
um there's a it's it's there's it's
related but it's not exactly the same
thing when one cell
defect so let's say an oncogene turns on
the cell closes all the gap junctions
disconnects from its neighbors
and now that computational boundary is
literally just that one cell
again it's not quite at the edge of the
cell because if you look at
the scale of things the cell is trying
to manage it's a little bit bigger than
that because it also really cares about
um some of the you know the the
nutrients the wastes the the con
specifics the
the prey whatever else is going on right
at that edge right so it's not
quite at the cell boundary so i i just
want to make that clear that this
diagram
isn't meant to be an anatomical uh
the cone isn't meant to be a map exactly
on the anatomy it's a cone of
the states that the thing is trying to
actively manage
yeah i think that the cones were
inflicted by us though
yeah but but you're absolutely right and
as soon as you did that i realized that
what would be good because that has to
be right those two diagrams eventually
have to meet
right and so there have to be there
there has to be a way to
so i think i don't know my visual um
imagination isn't great i have to think
a little bit more about a better way to
to kind of represent it but
of course you're right those two things
have to come together
yes stephen yeah i was just
so following on from what you were
saying is
often as well as useful when we think of
entities and processes
i'm maybe scaling up to more
psychological scales but
you know we often think about this is
this person this is
what this entity is diagnosed as and
this entity and
it's all kind of and and there's a lot
more now move towards
what's the process but then what kind of
processes do we have
on that continuum just like we're
talking about with the hurricane you
know
you maybe you've got a static entity
like a rock and then you've got your
kind of systems some of which could be
mechanical like a clock
but then you sort of hit structures
there's some sort of structure
like a i don't know like a skeleton or a
network of processes coming together
then you get into them which is what i
find really interesting with
the work you do is you the sort of
non-linear swarming
dynamics you know and it's sort of um
and i was wondering how
when you think of th you know you've got
a body and i'm a body and i'm trying to
work in my space around me so i see
things in my environment out there
and i can interact to some extent
depending on what my
available processes afford me in my
structures
and then there's other stuff inside
which to some extent i kind of have to
let
take care of themselves unless i want to
tattoo myself or do some sort of
internal
mutilation or something i'm curious
about
how this entity process
dynamic going in and out can be
thought of yeah um well i want to say a
couple of things
uh and again this is you know sort of
going going kind of far a stream but i
think i think it might be relevant
um when you say you are this body
sort of in the sense that we are talking
to the verbal
entity there but there are all sorts of
other entities there that we're not
hearing from that
that and so so we know that from split
brain patients right we know that
um after a commissurotomy the right side
of the brain
you can communicate with it it'll give
you opinions that uh
the verbal patient part of the patient
doesn't agree with doesn't know anything
about right so
it's really really interesting um i also
think about uh multiple personality you
know they call it
multiple personality disorder but but
but the reality is
you know a single a single brain body
system apparently can
post any number of distinct and how
in how i am i'm not a i'm not an expert
in this area i don't know how
psychologically deep so some of these
other personalities go but enough that
you can have a conversation certainly
enough that you can have a conversation
with them
which means they're doing better than
all of the ai that we've ever produced
right and and they uh and in fact i i
read once i forget where it was but
there was an interesting comment
from a a a therapist
who was asked to he was he was he was
asked to deal with
with a multiple personality patient and
he was talking about
integration and he was you know that the
goal of the therapy was going to
integrate because of course it's very
disruptive for the for the individual
and we're gonna we're gonna integrate
all of these into one
and one of the personalities said to
that patient
integration you you're gonna kill me
right that's what you're talking about i
thought you were a doctor what are we
talking about here
and so you know it was outraged that
that there was going to be this
integration of
you know of of of what at least uh
ostensibly uh you've got this entity
that certainly passes the turing test
and is
is not happy about the fact that you're
about to integrate it in you know away
basically right
so that's you know i think that goes
back to
this idea that we're an interpenetrating
set of
selves and we tend to only hear from the
verbal one
so there's all kinds of other ones in
there that are competing and
and cooperating and everything else and
and the other thing i can say about this
so that's more
questions than the answers i guess but
but the the other thing i think that's
interesting is that
you're you're right in the sense that um
the one kind of entity that we have
direct experience with which is the
verbal you know sort of one that
presumably we share is completely
ignorant of most of the things that are
going on
there and so the space that you're
working with nicely coarse grains over
all kinds of stuff you know your liver
function and everything else you don't
need to micromanage all this
however there are techniques that will
add
axes to your option space so if you
would like to learn
to also consciously control your heart
rate or your
skin temperature or whatever you can do
biofeedback there are tools that will
enable you to cross that that that
boundary
and you will now have a new axis in your
option space that you never did had
before
do you want it i don't know there's a
good reason why most of these you don't
you don't use it's as
good to sort of simplify your space but
but you know there was a there was an
it was a cool experiment where they uh
they measured the temperature between a
rat's
ears and they gave it a reward
proportional to the difference
in uh in temperature and so rats readily
learned to to get their ears to you know
i think like five degrees celsius or
something different between their ears
to get the reward right
so now that's amazing for a number of
reasons one is that okay now
now you've added uh an effector in your
space
that is is you know kind of this
physiological blood flow i don't know
how
they do it um that you didn't have
before the other thing of course is the
credit assignment
you know here you are you're a rat and
you just got some reward and so
well let me see why did i get this so
well my tail is pointing
up and my left you know fingers are
clenched and my whiskers are going which
of those things actually worries
right so so this is we still haven't
cracked this
in machine learning is how how living
things are so good at figuring out what
exactly they're being rewarded for small
number of trials actually
so but you can i think i think you can
break through at least to some extent
and you know break through
and actually even further right so there
are claims that certain types of um
you know mental practices will have
effects on your immune system for
example
right so you can i think you can go
pretty
far down right from if you wanted to add
these these kinds of things to your
option space
ah interesting actually just bouncing on
that going
that's really helpful actually i've not
even thought about that but that
that different parts of us ties in with
there's this big push all the time if
you say about integrate integrate
integrate
and actually scale out because i do a
lot of work with multi-service
um service providers say in africa or
other countries where they're
and you tend to find that any type of
um transdisciplinary project has the
problem about whichever regime of
attention or field of practice
the voice is in at that time and then
then when we talk about integrating but
it normally means
they dominate and what about configuring
so think about this idea of configuring
different fields of practice by
different ways or different ways of
knowing and also
ways the other voices is strategic
conversations with communities who don't
normally get a voice
who knows something in the state space
beyond what
the the actors who've got the job in the
agency know
and it's this sort of ties in a little
bit with what you're talking about here
so i think it's quite interesting in the
sense of
can we conf because in a way the biology
isn't trying to integrate
it's actually configuring and allowing
things to be but it has a way to still
know
their different teleological spaces and
either just let it get on with it or
yeah
knows where and when to get involved i
suppose is is the thing
yeah i mean so so so i think i think the
the one way of looking at that is to
is to ask what are the optimal policies
for uh for this binding so so i'll just
you know i'll give you an example so in
the case of in the case of the um
multicellularity we say
okay uh individual cells are pretty cool
but when they connect via gap junctions
into a multi-cellular collective they
can do these these marvelous things and
they resist cancer and
you know and and turning off the
connection and becoming met you know um
becoming a cancer cell and going
metastatic is is bad and so what you
would really like to do
is is to reconnect these cells back in
so the thing is
that right that that tightly coupling
individual units into a global entity
avails you of all kinds of interesting
things right so it raises the iq of the
whole and gives you all kinds of
capabilities
fine but one of the things that gets
lost when you do that
is uh that the larger system now now can
dominate
the the goals of the lower system and in
fact the larger system may have
very little uh care for the goals of the
welfare of the subunit
you know when was the last time you
worried about all the skin cells you're
shedding right you just you you know
you're gonna do what you're gonna do and
if you lose some skin cells you know no
no no problem
um so what that suggests is that
blood you know maximum maximizing out
this connectivity into some giant borg
like uh you know thing
is is an and obviously it's been you
know it's kind of been attempted on you
know on the
on the social scale we know how that
turns out so you want to
uh somewhere in between there there's a
there's an optimal policy
right where i i hope there may not you
know there may be some no-go theorem
it's
somewhere that says there is no good
policy but i hope
that somewhere in there there's a good
policy that allows us to
uh reap the rewards of appropriate kinds
of large-scale
organization without a sort of
blanket collectivism that that
completely uh sort of you know wipes out
the uh
the needs of the of the lower level
subunits so
that i hope is a is an empirical
question that we should we should be
looking for what kind of policies give
us
that that optimize the various things we
want to optimize
um josh vaughn garden i planned a grant
at one point
for this human flood this human
flourishing um program somewhere that i
think it's actually
an empirical question can we identify
the optimal policies that
preserve the needs of the subunits and
reap
the rewards of becoming a greater whole
nice so i learned this word yesterday at
gregor
it's the occult concept representing a
distinct non-physical
entity that arises from a collective
group of people
and i thought it was really cool and and
i think of this concept of
emergence so like at what level does
this collective
kind of body form and i don't know if
you've read the information theory of
individuality paper
uh by david krakauer but we really think
about you know emergence
you know like the emergence causing the
formation of the collective
entity but then there also has to be
like some kind of downward causation at
some some point in there like is so is
there
is this some kind of like critical point
like a phase transition that starts to
occur
or when does that kind of start to
happen that that bi-directional
information flow yeah
for sure i mean i mean th this this in
particular is is interesting because
i i i thought about this a little while
ago that you know especially
um people who are interested in this
kind of stuff uh
you know and you can think about the the
really old concept of group karma right
this idea that
that not only you have your own
individual cause and effect that you're
causing but but in a strong sense
the group of which you are apart has its
own right cause and effect
that is that is as real as so so
that idea and i don't know how many
thousands of years old that idea is
i think it is an amazing um amazingly
prescient because
in in western science the the you know
collective intelligence right the
science of collective intelligence and
this idea that right the group can be a
you know a swarm
of whatever can be an agent on its own
is relatively recent right that people
started taking that seriously in in
science
but i think i think that kind of
thinking must have been extremely
old because there are these traditions
that take it very seriously
that the group is not just a heap of
stuff
but it actually has its own agency in
the sense that it can even be the
subject of blame
and reward in the sense of you know the
sense of like rewarding punishment karma
whatever
that that that's a very strong view of
group agency that i think
we've only said you know scientifically
we've only really appreciated recently
so i think that's that's that's pretty
cool actually
random random linguistic thing here that
gregor i was thinking about egregious
and like egregious in my mind is like
out of bounds you know but and yet
gregor is or is not that it's the
opposite it's almost like a group
thing maybe maybe some other somebody
else can think about that differently
but i thought that was an interesting
conflict yeah very interesting
so i think about this concept of
collective karma
a lot um and really kind of whether or
not
like i have free will in the in the
present like
in terms of am i just some kind of
computation like my
like you know just because i've been
doing active inference and so
am i just my generative model that that
like effectively i can't make any
decision because
of of my model like whatever input i'm
getting at that moment
i have to decide based on on the the
condition of my model at that time
and i think about collective karma much
in the same way
um and whether or not there exists some
kind of of
agency in the present or or
not like if all the things that just
made me who
i am right now have just led ultimately
to
to be where i am and and in collective
karma too it's like a hurricane
that group of people caused that
hurricane to happen like they created
the causes for
the collective karma for the hurricane
to come um
so i don't know it's it's something that
that is really intriguing to me and
um you know
i don't know if you want to maybe
elaborate a little bit more on that
yeah yeah and and so and so two thoughts
about that
uh one one is that this goes back to
this idea of of spaces and the different
spaces that each of your um
each of the subunits is working in one
way that
and and after after i drew this cone and
i realized that it kind of looked like
the
the the special relativity cone and all
that uh
some other some other pieces of
relativity sort of
started started popping into my head and
this idea of
deforming the space around you right so
if you're a mass you deform the space
around you which in turn
alters your next possible movements and
the possible movements of the other
masses around you right
so by deforming that by your actions you
are deforming the possible
the possibility space for for your for
yourself for things next to you for your
components and so on
and so one thing that i think happens is
that these larger systems
deform the action space for their lower
systems
so that to that so but all they have to
do is
roll downhill in effect and so if you
zoom in
so this gets back and i'm going to
connect this back to your your point
about karma
and and action and choices and so on
when you zoom in
all you see is physics and you see and
you say oh well this
this is yellow of course that's what
it's doing that's all it could do all
the gradients are pointing this way
that's what it had to do
but the reason it can be it can do that
is and still get to some global goal is
because the higher level system has
already deformed that space
so i see this and i don't know how i'm
going to ever draw this that's a
different story but but i see all these
different levels
as uh deforming their simpler space that
they're working in
which then changes the option space for
their sub units
so that they can they don't have to be a
smart this is
this is sort of bennett's idea of you
know progressively dumber robots all the
way down
that works if each system makes it so
that so that the the
the lower level systems don't have to do
quite as much of the work and there's a
stupid example i always go to from from
you know
from like common everyday life if if if
you ever had a friend who tried to stop
smoking
and they like to smoke at night one of
the things they might do is put their
car key someone that's really hard to
get to
why because they know that when they you
know at midnight when they want to smoke
they're not going to feel like going
hunting for the keys and then they could
find and then that's that so
so what they're doing is you know who
are you doing this so you're doing this
to your future self right you're
deforming the space for your future self
in that case consciously and of course
we all do things unconsciously too
but in that case you're consciously
deforming the action space
for your future self in order to uh so
that you can be on autopilot at that
point right you don't have to have the
willpower at midnight that i'm gonna
not do this it's you've already
somebody's already sort of twisted the
space for you so that
just going to get your keys is just too
high of a barrier and then forget it
so uh right so so i think i think that
that
that that deformation of these action
spaces is a really important way in
which
um lower and higher level systems relate
the lower level systems simplify the
action space for the higher level system
because they're competent so the higher
level system doesn't need all the
dimensions
and the higher system bends the space of
the lower system to make things easier
to get to and that and that goes back to
your other point that you that you just
made about
um in the moment of of of taking actions
in the moment that are
the consequence of all the pressures
that you have set up and other
things have set up for you where yeah i
see this as those
so if we think about will in the sense
of you know free will or decision making
or whatever
i i see this again this like uh
four dimensional block where each one of
us at any point in time is a slice of it
and if you zoom in on that one that that
self-lit
that exists at that one time slice your
your uh free will so to speak is
is limited to none because at that
moment on the local scale
you you are going to do whatever the
local forces have arranged that you're
going to do right
and and this is the one like a simple
example is you know can you control what
your next thought is going to be
you really can't your next thought is
going to be whatever it is so at the
local
at the local level when you zoom in you
know
there's there's no no useful sense of
freedom there however
if you zoom out on the long scale what
you what is true
i think is that you can take actions
repeated actions whether they be
practice or or you know whatever they're
going to be
you can take repeated actions that alter
your
cognitive causal structure so that over
time
you have made changes and so so no you
can't control the next thought you're
going to have now
but you can control what percentage of
your thoughts are negative or whatever
whatever it is down down the line right
so so to me that question of of choice
and and freedom
is very much relative to what scale
you're asking but if you zoom in to the
to the
to the lower you know to the to the
physics and the sort of short time scale
no i don't think there's any useful
sense of that but over the long term
absolutely
because you can make changes both in
your environment your own structure
that will get you to a different place
thanks uh stephen yeah this is really
helpful actually to
hear it thought about this way and just
as we're saying there about
this sort of almost transcendental um
or the the way we often think of things
being excluded
egregious as sarah was saying and
um when we we need to move beyond
um the inner outer you know there's an
inner thought process and there's an
outer world but the two are linked like
we say so with active inference
the idea is that i don't necessarily
purely have a model
of those cones in my head i i
i've got an action model for how to draw
them
i haven't got the whole thing that can
be dumped down like a data source but i
have a way to
do that which sort of ties in and i was
one and
when you mentioned there about looking
at the future
one thing that adds that active
inference hasn't really done is it
talks about say the car keys example is
is
is the sequence at which something might
have to happen to get to the future
being disrupted which is kind of that
quantum contextuality
idea whereas normally in active
influence they talk about the
niche construction or the niche
modification but
it's not just about modifying itself
it's modifying
the trajectories you might take through
that niche
which that that gives you more near
time possibilities for like sculpting
what can happen when it can happen so
that i think that's quite
useful i was wondering how how you see
that relationship to niche construction
and
weather and models being sort of
embedded in the world i.e so if systems
are really models in the world
that we then read or interact with and
using our structures how do we
how do we link up that kind of cone with
the kind of
niche construction that's maybe being
used in other areas of active imprints
yeah i mean so that's that's a very
difficult
question i can sort of address a small
part of it i think at this point
and i can j you know i think i think one
of the key
questions of all of this is to what
extent
when we look at systems and we see the
dimensions with
let's just do the third person case
first and then we'll
talk about that i think the first person
case that you're talking about so when
we look at a system
and we make a map of its its problem
solving in some space and its goal
directed activity in some space
the question is uh is that in any sense
objective in the meaning meaning could
we um
could we make a case that that that
model of that space
is better or the best or is
uh is there an infinity of ways to look
at it and in particular
how does that relate to now the first
person perspective of that that system
itself
what does the space look like it's it's
a little bit like um
you know the the the whole um belt thing
right where
you're sort of in some space what does
it look like to you and
chris fields made a really nice example
uh in our um
computational meeting a couple weeks ago
where you said imagine
imagine a bacterium and there's some
sugar gradient
that that the bacterium is in and it's
you know it wants to have more energy
so now one thing we are tempted to do is
to draw
a space where by rotating its flagella
and whatever else
this thing is going to move up the
gradient but there's something else it
can do which is that it can turn on a
gene for an enzyme that lets it use
a completely different sugar or let it
use that sugar
better or something else that solves
that same problem
with an effector that to us is an
entirely different space
so so so we look at this and we say ah
that solution has a problem in um in
physical space and it has a solution in
transcriptional space if you're a
bacterium
is there any sense in which those are
not part of the same space i mean i have
no idea what it's right obviously what
it's like to be that bacterium
one could make an argument that our
dissection of these things has two
different spaces
is is totally biased because that's
where scientists and we like to look at
things that to the bacterium both of
those
are effectors that live together that's
kind of a mix
it's almost like um you know it's almost
like you you can ask about uh
some sort of pca right if you're a
principal component analysis where
you're learning about your world and
you're going to end up with a picture of
what the axes are
that don't necessarily make any sense to
us looking at the system right
you find you get you get these
components that you know these control
knobs and we look at
what the hell is the you know what is it
doing well but but but but to the system
those are efficient
ways to build an axis and people like um
you know robert brittner and don hoffman
have these models of these cognitive
systems from scratch sort of
building these worlds to these virtual
spaces for themselves right
that you don't actually know what spaces
you're in so
um i think there's a research agenda
there which is
can we build some sort of appliance
meaning some sort of i don't know
machine learning thing or something
that will try to extract these
in a i'm not going to say unbiased but
at least unsupervised manner
that can we build an agency detector can
we build something that looks at a
system
and says i tell you what if you assume
this
axis this axis and this axis then i can
paint you a really
uh efficient uh search strategy that
will allow you to predict
what the system is going to do next
because we can view this as problem
solving in this space
right and maybe and maybe it generates a
palette of um
solutions like that and there's one
that's head and shoulders above the
others and you say fine that's my
scientific theory of what's going on
here
and and maybe right and maybe that works
i don't know so so that's that's
that's a research kind of agenda for the
future and
the other cool thing about that is if
you
if you do that of course one thing you
might want to do is then
build a more sophisticated
uh synthetic intelligence by sticking
that thing
basically closing the loop and sticking
that that module inside the agent itself
and here's why i'm saying that all
animals
i think uh you know at least past a
certain point
certainly have agency detectors this is
why we love our visual systems love
symmetry and so on because
you really want to know looking out into
the world you really want to know
what are the passive elements and what
are the other agents
that might eat you that you might
communicate with that you might convince
them to do something else
so so we are constantly estimating
um you know theory of mind right an
agency for all the things we're looking
at
because because that helps you get
around you you need to know if
if it's if it's a rock or if it's
something that's just going to come eat
you no matter what or if it's a con
specific that you might actually lie to
and or or you don't have a relationship
whatever you're going to do some sort of
complicated
interaction right so we're all we're all
trying to gauge that and
probably where what what what one of the
things that kind of module
also does is turn inwards to tell you
stories about yourself
and the reason we know that exists is
because of confabulation
so just as a simple example as this is
the modern there
there are older examples from the brain
split brain studies but the modern
example
there's um there's somebody who's got an
electrode and this was an actual
experiment
that was done he had epilepsy or
something and they put an electrode in
their brain and in his brain and it
didn't
happen to land in an area that when you
stimulate it it stimulates laughter
the person just starts laughing right so
so so you're sitting there so this this
person is sitting there talking to
you know having a serious conversation
with the doctor somebody off scene
pushes the button person starts laughing
the doctor says to him why are you
laughing zero percent of the time
the answer is geez i don't know that was
super weird i was all serious and
suddenly my mouth starts laughing that
never happens what happens is the person
says
oh i came up with a funny story and i
was just thinking of a funny thing that
happened
right so what happens is and this has
been you know i'm not the first person
to point this out
that we are massively unaware
of lots of stuff that goes on in there
and we have a module apparently
whose job it is to tell coherent stories
about what that all adds up to
so not not just turning outwards to see
what kind of
agents we see out there but actually to
look inwards and come up with plausible
explanations that no you're not an
automaton because somebody pushed a
button
that's not that that's not a preferred
explanation the preferred explanation is
you're an agent you come up with funny
stories and sometimes they made you
laugh that's a better explanation
so um so so we have this so so if we had
such a thing we could imagine already
piece by piece
uh starting to put this together into
what
might be a fairly sophisticated
cognitive system that has a bit of
metacognition and a bit of
uh much like all of us uh sort of faulty
access to what it is that we're doing
and and all these kind of interesting
things
nice so i'm going to kind of take it
back to this
um time space cube because i just
really can't wrap my mind around the
fact that if you slice up the cube i
think about it like a like a confocal
z stack so if you have a slice that's
the present
if i can't change this slice like you
know you can take a projection
of the confocal image and look at the
whole picture if i can't change this one
slice
how is it that i'm going to change the
future right so all the slices up until
this point
lead me to make this current existing
slice and then
it do i can i change any point in the
future i don't see how that's possible
if i can't change
the point in the present so are we just
like i think about we had shanna dobson
and
chris fields on and we were talking
about express you know compressing and
expanding
time and space um and just time in all
kinds of
contexts like is it even a construct or
how does it work
and like non-archimedean time and all
that stuff
so i don't know what uh if you want to
maybe unpack that a little bit for me
because i'm just not kind of
seeing the possibility of um
of this changing the future without
being able to change the present
yeah totally possible and so and so for
sure i'm not going to try to
make the argument that uh we have a um
a mature theory of you know free will of
that of that kind i don't think we do
but
um and i think you're absolutely right
in that that is in fact
a really critical point if if if if your
freedom
in each slice is zero then many times
zero it's still zero right so
totally totally true i i think we can
make two moves and again this is this is
super
early i you know i'm not claiming this
is in any way gonna survive uh get a
careful
careful thought into the future um i
think we can make two
shifts one shift is that i think
it's a again and again i'm like a broken
record with this stuff but but i think i
think that binary
um this binary distinction between you
have
freedom or you do not i think that's
wrong so so i think what you have
it goes by amounts so so
you may have very little you know if
you're if you're if you're a
mechanical clock you have very little
and uh
if you're some other type of living
thing you may have more and then you may
have more than that
so then what you have is and this is
super super amateurish but but just to
kind of visualize
what i see is the kind of um addition
that you get in calculus
where you start with extremely tiny
things that are
kind of zero but not really and
eventually they add up to something
right that's how i see it that's how i
think that what you have at each point
is a teeny tiny amount and if you look
close
you know basically it's an epsilon
that's not worth talking about it's
basically you don't have any
but it isn't quite zero and over time
that
mental effort whatever that is that you
put into you know
working on your free will or on your
kindness or whatever you're working on
over time it integrates into an area
even though
you're integrating infinitely thin
strips like that's
that's the vision that i have in my head
that if we just do away with the fact
that it's actually zero but i don't
think it's actually zero
then you can build up something over
time and you can and you can magnify
and if you know i'll say one more thing
which if we're gonna if we're gonna
abuse physics like this right which i
mean i realize this is all like
completely informal and whatever
if we're gonna abuse it um i'll make
i'll make one more one more analogy
if you think about what is the
uh what what is a minimal level of
agency so so so sometimes people ask
me like um well is there a zero on your
on your
continuum right is there an actual zero
like what's the minimum what is the
smallest
and so i think okay if you're going to
pick if you're going to design the
absolute
minimal piece that still has some
non-zero agency what does it need i feel
like it needs two things
it needs some minimal amount of
uh decision making that isn't obviously
caused by local causes right it needs at
least
something that is that reaches outward
in terms of space or time or complexity
or something
that isn't obviously a locally
determined
um you know necessity that that's one
and the second thing it needs is some
amount of goal directed
activity something that looks like uh a
goal directed activity
so so once you've said that it seems to
me that that
individual particles already have this
right because because quantum
indeterminacy gives you the first one
and least action principles give you the
second so you've already got that and so
now
when you so so i think and again this is
you know amateurish as far as the
physics goes but my gut feeling is
that there isn't a zero that you already
start with
some minimal amount and now you can do
one of two things you can see you got
these
you got these particles you can do one
of two things you can you can make a
rock
out of them so you aggregate them in a
in in one way
which basically uh gets rid of all those
nice properties and
it and and it and it ends up having
having you know very low agency it
doesn't it you know it just it just
aggregates all of it in a way that
doesn't do anything useful or
if you're if you're alive you can uh you
can amplify those properties and end up
you know further down on the on the
continuum so that's kind of
my fuzzy story at the moment is that i
think we start off
at non-zero and then you can either
stay there if you don't have the right
organization or you can amplify the hell
out of it and
and get to you know to get to be more
agential
nice thanks i definitely think that uh
non-zero is the right answer
so we've got uh maybe like 15 minutes
left
and um you know i just there's some
closing thoughts some room for
some last minute questions uh sarah or
steven do you have any
last minute things you want to ask
no my head has sufficiently exploded
yeah no i think i think that was a night
i mean i think there's a lot to think
about because we've covered an awful lot
of territory but um
i think i think it's it was interesting
to see that you're bringing the
thingness
and um that i know carl fristen talks
about that
um so i i suppose one last bit would be
would you call yourself um a non-dual
modest in the way that um carl
talks about that idea or is that
something a bit different or maybe not
even relevant in this context
yeah that's that's a good that's a good
question so so i hesitate to put a name
on it for for two reasons number one
um everything that we've talked about so
far
has been very much from a functional
third person perspective so so we
haven't really touched
the the so-called hard problem of
consciousness or what the
so in order and the thing is nothing
that i've said
touches this question of why is it like
to be something that's one of these
systems right
so from that perspective assuming that
we believe i mean some people you know
will say that that's a non-problem and
that there is no such thing and then
whatever
but i i i'm not 100 convinced of that
actually and
from so so so there are that i i do
think there's a hard problem and i don't
have anything that addresses it
and so uh i don't know
you know what camp that puts me in the
other the other thing is that
um i have a lot of um sort of
uh uh kind of pan psychist sympathies in
the following way
so i think that if you scale
down if you if you so so so what's one
reason people don't like pancyth
it means that you know it means that you
think that rocks they have hopes and
dreams like the rest of us okay so
that's obviously
not what i'm saying the reason people go
to that
to that extreme is because they've
scaled down
the structures that are needed for
agency but they haven't scaled down the
expectation
so so that's so yes it's it's silly to
to think that rocks and dreams have to
that rocks have the same hopes and
dreams that we do however
if you scale both sides of the equation
i'm not at all sure why again if you
don't if you if you're not into binary
classifications it is conscious or it's
not
that that i think is definitely wrong so
if if phenomenal consciousness is a kind
of um
continuum too i don't see any reason why
there couldn't be a tiny
bit of something that's super hard for
us to imagine because we're used to a
much a much bigger level of
perception and consciousness that that
isn't associated with
a lot of other systems that we normally
that you know that the people who
normally work in cognitive science would
never buy as
as as as having consciousness so so so i
have a lot of
you know kind of sympathies on that
front mainly because i don't buy this
binary distinction
um and we could talk about this actually
interesting
i don't even i i'll tell you why
basically um
bioengineering and the kinds of things
that are possible
now are they they are really dissolving
a lot of things that seem to be
uh sharp categories before and i'm not
even sure
at this point that um the distinction
between first person and third person
knowledge
is even sharp and and i'll just i'll
just draw you a simple picture
and i preface this by saying um i i made
a picture of this and i sent it to a um
a well-known philosopher and he said it
was you know horrible horrible and
and uh and uh and not not useful but but
we'll see
we'll see what you think um imagine that
uh
you're looking at that there's a brain
and there's some electrophysiology
being done some electrodes stuck in
there and that's it's being processed
and you're
and you're on the outside you're the
scientist you're on the outside you're
looking at that data
uncontroversially third person right you
have no idea what it's like to be that
subject
you are studying some signals that come
off of that line
now what we do is we change this
we change the scenario a little bit and
uh what we do is we take
some of those interfaces that you know
they have these interfaces for the blind
that either go on your tongue
or they go sometimes in your retina but
basically they turn
uh camera signals into something that's
directly
plugged into your brain with electrodes
okay so now we we take that setup and
instead of the camera we plug it
directly into the electrophysiology
apparatus
so now what you're receiving is you're
receiving a heavily processed
signal but it's coming directly from
that brain into your brain and what's
interesting is that people who use these
kind of sensory augmentation devices
they will eventually report that it's
just like seeing they learn to get
around like the electric lollipop is
this thing you stick on your tongue
and it shocks your tongue in a way that
um maps onto the pixels of a camera
right and they say oh it's just like
seeing it
so uh so okay so now you've moved so you
know it's like um
uh it's it's sort of you know third
person
but you know it's maybe like 2.5 percent
or something
and then you can do another experiment
you can say well what we're going to do
is instead of using
all this um like uh
heavily electric you know all this
electronics and
and processing uh in between we're just
going to connect the brains
and we can and we can do this and the
reason we know we can do this
is that there are conjoined twins whose
brains are in fact connected
so that there's no you know sort of sort
of
clumsy electronic interface in the
middle the brains are directly connected
and so now you say okay so if i'm now if
my brain is now connected to this other
person having the experience
it's sort of am i is that still third
person and then you ask the question
yeah but
in your own brains of some people say ah
that's an aberrant you know that's an
aberrant case
but in your own brain you've got pieces
of the brain that have to talk to each
other you're not an indivisible monad of
some type right you are
a bunch of pieces that also have to talk
to each other so the left side has to
talk to the right side in fact the front
talks to the brain
you are anyway pieces of the brain
having to talk to each other
and somehow that ends up being first
person so now what we've just done is
built
a continuum where you can smoothly and
we can fill in anywhere between these
two systems i can fill in as
as you know sort of finely as you want
and you can smoothly move from from
first person experience to third person
is
science because the bioengineering tells
you that you can do it
so so i'm not even sure that's a you
know i'm not sure that's a distinction
so i i you know it's hard to say
uh anyway that's a long winded answer to
your question
wow i i was gonna ask one question now
i'm gonna ask another one
um this makes me think you know like
related to core screening related to
layers and levels of
of uh different organisms like
it just what you the kind of example you
just laid out
you know makes me question whether you
can even stratify
in that way or whether it makes sense to
stratify in that way
um but let me go back to um
something we didn't cover and and i i
heard it on your podcast
and um you ended with a question
related to moral philosophy um or ethics
i guess not even
i don't know the distinction there but
yeah
um i mean when
you know if you're coming from the
perspective of not
believing in a binary uh between
you said it better than i did living
non-living whatever like agent versus
not
um and then you're making things like
xenobots it's like
that kind of if that's if you held those
two views
um of not believing in the binary then
there it seems like there really
wouldn't be an ethical question and so
i'm wondering where your
where your thinking is along that yeah
no no i think i think there's definitely
an ethical question
uh and and i think it's not quite what
we think it is but and i'll tell you
what it is but let's just let's just
take a step back so
so long before anybody made xenobots
we made humans right the old-fashioned
way
and so this is like uh you know then
it's competence without comprehension
right so we have no idea how it worked
but for for
you know hundreds of thousands of years
we made other humans and so
we take care of them as best we can most
of the time sometimes
not really very well you know so so so
we already did that
then uh we make all sorts of
animals in terms of um of food
production and other things
we make hybrids so we make mules that
are animals that never existed before
right we make uh we've made new new
plants
so so so the first thing that's really
critical and and
often the the reason i'm sort of
sensitized to all this is the people
always say
oh my god you're making xenobots it's a
new like
let's not let's not forget what we've
already been doing right and
let's let's be super clear that that
this is a massive problem with the with
the food industry right
long before we get to worrying about
zenobots there's all kinds of things
that that we need to fix so
i just want to be you know i kind of
want to be clear that we've already been
making
animals and in fact other humans for
which we sometimes take good
responsibility and sometimes
we we don't i think i think this is
absolutely uh
raises an ethical problem and the
ethical problem is is the following
when we um when we go to uh
synthetic biology and and bioengineering
kinds of seminars
there's usually now a session that's
about ethics
and the session goes like this somebody
will show
a brain organoid made of human cells and
someone will say
oh my god that you shouldn't be doing
that and somebody else
will say well let's just see how much
like a human brain it is and then they
and then people spend a couple hours
arguing about whether it is or is not
enough like a human brain that they need
to worry about it and maybe they end up
saying it's fine or maybe they end up
saying it's not fine but
i think the much bigger issue is that
whether or not something looks anything
like a human brain
is a very poor guide to how much you
need to worry about it
and in the past uh the way that you
the way that we would figure out whether
or not how much
moral responsibility we have for a
particular system went roughly like this
you would sort of look at it and and if
it was
um squishy and and and warm and
furry you would say yeah and if it was
metallic
and you know and it came from an
assembly line you'd say do what you want
no problem right
so so two two things used to be a guide
and even that
we didn't do so well we can't obviously
with those principles but but the two
things that used to be a guide were
where did it come from did it evolve or
was it designed
and what is it what is it made of and
and it was a pr
and that was pretty good right you could
yeah if
because if it was evolved you could look
on the sort of the
the tree of life and you could say it's
a worm
we don't need to fill out any forms when
we do these experiments or you could say
it's a frog i need to fill out a lot of
forms before we can do experiments right
for that then that's in fact
how it works because you have because
you know something about that
that lineage and you make some sort of
guesses about where
things are and then if it's an octopus
people really don't know what to do and
then so on
all of that is going completely out the
window right so in the next
uh in the next i don't know a couple of
decades we are going to be surrounded by
and this is another thing that i'm
writing on the option space of possible
creatures we're talking about
uh hybrids cyborgs hybrids there's a
million different ways to recombine
evolved designed living non-living and
software agents
into new forms that have never existed
before
so what something looks like is no guide
to
what the cognition is where it came from
meaning if all the design
is going to be a bad question because
half of the stuff we're building with is
now
evolved and and so on um all of the
things you know it's just a machine
versus oh but you know it's a nice
mammal all that stuff is going to go out
the window
so to me the ethical problem is much
bigger
than just asking about whether
something's like a human brain the
what we really are going to need is a
new
ethical system for learning how to deal
with agents that look
nothing like us and that don't look like
anything we've ever seen before
and yet are going to have all sorts of
cognitive capacities
and uh we have to let go of categories
like machine
like robot like um all these other
things that really don't mean anything
they never did but before but it was
fine in the past it's no longer
going to be useful um and that's that's
the ethical
that's the ethical problem
uh so great so i'm gonna go stare at a
wall and try to integrate this
information
uh it was a lot um
thank you so much for coming on thank
you so much yeah this was really fun
yeah
great the great great discussion thank
you so much
thanks thank you bye